Guide to Rabbi Arthur Schneier Papers TAM.694
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Rabbi Arthur Schneier Papers
1960-2012
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Schneier, Arthur, Rabbi
TAM.694
106.75 Linear Feet in 82 record cartons, 9 manuscript boxes, 1 half manuscript box, 4 oversize flat boxes, and 1 small flat box
Rabbi Arthur Schneier lived under Nazi occupation in Budapest until age 17 and immigrated to the United States in 1947. In 1955, Schneier received his rabbinical ordination from Yeshiva University. He has served as the Senior Rabbi of New York City's Park East Synagogue. Schneier has been an active member and leader of prominent international religious and political relations' councils. This collection consists of materials created and collected by Rabbi Arthur Schneier in the course of his personal and professional life as a rabbi and activist concerned with international religious freedom and human rights efforts. Materials include correspondence, photographs, memoranda, subject files on various countries, and other materials concerning his involvement with the Foreign Service Institute and his international trips, with particular emphasis on China and the Soviet Union. The collection also includes materials documenting his participating in the Appeal of Conscience Foundation and their annual awards dinner.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was donated by Rabbi Arthur Schneier in 2017. The accession numbers associated with this gift are 2017.035, 2017.067, and 2017.075.
Arrangement
The arrangement of the collection and titles of each series are based on the original order of the records as maintained by Rabbi Arthur Schneier and Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives' Curator, Michael Koncewicz. Original folder titles were retained. Routine financial statements, duplicate publications, and documents with sensitive personal information were removed. The collection is organized into eight (8) series: Series 1: Foreign Service Institute (FSI); Series 2: Correspondence; Series 3: Clippings; Series 4: Annual Award Dinner (AAD); Series 5: Country Files; Series 6: Photographs; Series 7: Conference Files; Series 8: Internal Alliance of Civilizations (AoC) Records/Miscellaneous.
Biographical Note
Rabbi Arthur Schneier (1930- ) was born on March 20, 1930 in Vienna, Austria, and lived under Nazi occupation in Budapest until age 17. Schneier immigrated to the United States in 1947. He graduated with a Bachelor of Arts from Yeshiva University in 1951 and earned a Masters of Arts from New York University in 1953. In 1955, Schneier received his rabbinical ordination from Yeshiva University. He has served for over 50 years as the Senior Rabbi of New York City's Park East Synagogue. Over the years, he has been an active member of many prominent religious and political relations' councils including: the Council on Foreign Relations, United Nations Development Corporation, and the United States Holocaust Memorial Museum committee. Schneier serves as Vice President of the World Jewish Congress American Section. Schneier encourages interfaith dialogue, cultural understanding, and the religious freedom for all citizens of the world.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of materials created and collected by Rabbi Arthur Schneier in the course of his personal and professional life as a rabbi and activist concerned with international religious freedom and human rights efforts. Materials include correspondence, photographs, memoranda, subject files on various countries, and other materials concerning his involvement with the Foreign Service Institute and his international trips, with particular emphasis on China and the Soviet Union. The collection also includes materials documenting his participating in the Appeal of Conscience Foundation and their annual awards dinner.
United States -- Foreign relations.; China; Jews -- Soviet Union; Religion and social problems.; Politics and culture.; Faxes.; Clippings files.; International relations.
- Foreign Service Institute (F.S.I.)
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains documents, booklets and information pretaining to Foreign Service Institute (F.S.I.) seminars ranging from 1981-2011.
  - Foreign Service Institute (F.S.I.) Seminar, 1981-1991 (Box 1)
  - Foreign Service Institute (F.S.I.) Seminar, 1992-2007 (Box 2)
  - Foreign Service Institute (F.S.I.), 1995-1996 (Box 3)
  - Foreign Service Institute (F.S.I.), 1997 (Box 4)
  - Foreign Service Institute (F.S.I.), 1998-1999 (Box 5)
  - Foreign Service Institute (F.S.I.), 2009-2011 (Box 6)
- Correspondence/Faxes
  This series consists of correspondence and faxes which range from 1975-2012. There are documents regarding the Appeal of Conscience Foundation (AoC), international relations, and general correspondence between Rabbi Arthur Schneier and his contacts.
  - Correspondence and Annual Award Dinner (A.A.D.) Invites, 1975-1976 (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1980-1989 (Box 9)
  - AoC Correspondence, 1982-1990 (Box 10)
  - Faxes, 1990-1992 (Box 11)
  - AoC Correspondence, 1991-1994 (Box 12)
  - Faxes, 1992 (Box 13)
  - Faxes, 1993-1995 (Box 14, Box 15)
  - Contacts and Communications, 1993 (Box 16)
  - Faxes, 1994 (Box 17)
  - Faxes, 1995-1999 (Box 18, Box 19)
  - Correspondence, 2000-2010 (Box 20)
  - Correspondence Organizations, 2000-2010 (Box 21)
  - Correspondence Countries, 2000-2010 (Box 22)
  - Faxes, 2000-2002 (Box 23)
  - Faxes, 2002-2003 (Box 24)
  - Faxes, 2004 (Box 25)
  - Faxes/Correspondence, 2004-2010 (Box 26)
  - Faxes/ACF Handouts Binder, 2005 (Box 27)
  - Faxes, 2005-2007 (Box 28)
  - Correspondence Countries, 2005-2011 (Box 29)
  - Correspondence Spain, 2005-2008 (Box 30)
  - Holiday Messages, 2005-2009 (Box 31)
  - Faxes and Correspondence, 2012 (Box 32)
  - Rabbi Arthur Schneier Personal Correspondence, 1970s-1980s (Box 33)
- Clippings
- Annual Award Dinner (A.A.D.)
  This series contains materials regarding various Annual Award Dinners (A.A.D.) ranging from 1975-2012. The materials consist of luncheon and dinner programs, correspondence, and award announcements.
  - Annual Award Dinners (A.A.D.), 1966-1980 (Box 44, Box 45)
  - Award Dinner, 1970-1979 (Box 46)
  - Award Dinner/Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1977 (Box 47)
  - Annual Award Luncheon, 1994 (Box 56)
  - Annual Award Dinner (A.A.D.), 1995 (Box 57)
  - Annual Award Dinner (A.A.D.), 1996 (Box 58)
  - Annual Award Dinner (A.A.D.), 1998-1999 (Box 59)
  - Annual Award Dinner (A.A.D.), 2000 (Box 60)
  - Annual Award Dinner (A.A.D.), 2001 (Box 61)
  - Annual Award Dinner (A.A.D.), 2010 (Box 70)
  - Annual Award Dinner (A.A.D.), 2010-2011 (Box 71)
- Country Files
  - Countries, I-Morocco, 1970-1993 (Box 74)
  - Romania, 1979-1992 (Box 80)
  - China, 1990s (Box 87)
  - Israel, 1990s (Box 89)
  - China, 1998-1999 (Box 96)
- Photographs
  The photographs depict various religious leader and political conferences as well as Rabbi Arthur Schneier meeting with prominent world leaders.
  - Photo Albums 1960s -1970s (Box 111, Box 112)
    - Photo album, 1954-1967; cuid2602 (Box 111)
  - Photo Albums, After 1970 (Box 113)
  - Flood in Romania Photo Albums, 1970 (Box 114)
  - Photo Albums, 1970 (Box 116)
  - Photographs, 1990-1991 (Box 122)
  - Miscellaneous Photographs, 1992-1993 (Box 125)
  - Moscow Trips, 1993-1995 (Box 126)
  - Israel, 1993-1994 (Box 127)
  - Conferences, 1994-1995 (Box 128, Box 133)
  - China Trip, 1994-1995 (Box 129)
  - Photos Miscellaneous, 2003-2004 (Box 142)
  - Photos (Box 150)
  - Over sized Photograph (Box 191)
- Conference Files
  This series consists of documents regarding international conferences including: Berne Conference, Bosphorus Conference, Kosovo Conference, Macedonia Conference, the World Economic Forum, and Peace and Tolerance.
  - Berne Conference, 1992 (Box 151)
  - Bosphorus Conference, 1994 (Box 152)
  - Kosovo Conference, 1999 (Box 153)
  - Macedonia Conference, 2003 (Box 154)
  - World Economic Forum, 2004 (Box 155)
  - Peace and Tolerance II, 2005 (Box 156)
- Appeal of Conscience Foundation (AoC) Records/Miscellaneous
  This series consists of invitations, Rabbi Arthur Schneier's schedules, Books of Moses, event programs, and copies of speeches ranging from 1970-2012.
  - Appeal of Conscience (Soviet Jewry), 1965-1971 (Box 157)
    - 1966 USSR mission, cuid2594 (Box 157)
    - Notes, 1965-1971; cuid2593 (Box 157)
    - Program services -- Ambassador George V. Allen symposium, 1967; cuid2601 (Box 157)
    - Program services -- Correspondence, 1965; cuid2596 (Box 157)
    - Program services -- Russian Jewry protests -- "An Appeal of Consciences" advertisement, 1965; cuid2595 (Box 157)
    - Program services -- Russian Jewry protests -- Bronze plaque, 1964-1965; cuid2597 (Box 157)
    - Program services -- Russian Jewry protests -- Dedication of plaque, correspondence, transcripts of speeches, 1964-1965; cuid2598 (Box 157)
    - Program services -- "You Are Not Forsaken, Soviet Jewry", 1965-1966; cuid2599 (Box 157)
    - USSR Soviet Jewry protests, 1966; cuid2600 (Box 157)
  - Miscellaneous, 1970-1980 (Box 159, Box 160)
  - Books of Moses Moscow, 1977 (Box 163, Box 164)
  - Miscellaneous, 1978-1983 (Box 165)
  - Awards and Honors, 1980-1995 (Box 166)
  - Miscellaneous, 1984-2007 (Box 167)
  - Schedules/Miscellaneous Contributions, 2009-2011, 1987-2012 (Box 168)
  - Miscellaneous, 1987-2006 (Box 169)
  - Invitations, 1987-1994 (Box 170)
  - White House/Other Politics, 1988-1992 (Box 171)
  - Rabbi Arthur Schneier Schedules, 1989-2004 (Box 172)
  - Programs, 1992-1999 (Box 173)
  - Awards and Honors, 1996-2002 (Box 174)
  - United Nations Alliance of Civilizations (UNAoC) (Box 177, Box 178, Box 179, Box 180)
  - Speeches & Events (Box 181, Box 182, Box 183, Box 184)
  - U.S. Commission, 1993-2005 (Box 187)
  - Unlabeled Boxes (Box 188, Box 189, Box 190)